Let me introduce our
speaker for today.
We are delighted
to have Vivek, who
is a research scientist at
Google DeepMind, leading
research at the intersection
of AI, Science, and Medicine.
He is the lead researcher
behind Med-PaLM
and Med-PaLM 2, the
first AI systems
to obtain passing
and expert-level
scores on US medical
license exam, respectively.
Vivek also co-leads project
AMIE, a research program
aiming to build and democratize
medical superintelligence.
And prior to Google, he worked
on multimodal assistant systems
at Facebook AI
research, and he is also
part of the faculty for
executive education at Harvard
TH Chan School of Public Health.
Let's welcome him.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you, Karan Thank you
to the course organizers.
And thank you,
everyone, for coming in
and sorry for not
starting exactly on time.
But hopefully, this will
be a useful session.
And yeah, today I
want to be telling you
about some of the
work that we've
been doing over
the past few years
at the intersection of
agentic AI systems and science
and medicine.
The underlying
theme of this work
is to build out generally
capable and general-purpose AI
systems that can act as
collaborative partners
for experts in the scientific
and medical domain,
that is, namely
scientists and doctors.
So the first project I want
to be telling you about
is this effort
called co-scientist.
So the system that we're
trying to build out over here,
the mission for this work
is to essentially build out
a collaborative
partner for scientists
and the hope is that
with this system,
we can really
accelerate the clock
speed of scientific and
biomedical discoveries
and really give scientists
superpowers to do
the work that they are doing.
And it's funny because
this work actually
has its genesis in
a talk that I gave
at Stanford a few years back.
So I think, as Karan
mentioned, back in 2023,
we had this paper
published in Nature
where we introduced this large
language model called Med-PaLM.
So Med-PaLM was one of the first
examples of a medically tuned
large language model.
So we built out the
system to do well on tasks
medical question-answering
and summarization.
And back then, it was
one of the first systems
to do well on this
benchmark, which
was reflective of US medical
license exam-style questions.
So it was one of the first
models to reach passing level
and then later on a future
version of the system,
reach like expert-level
scores on this benchmark.
So that made headline results.
So I think it was like October
2023 when I was at Stanford,
and I was actually giving
a talk on that system.
And at the end of
the talk, there
was this one professor
over here, Dr. Gary Peltz.
And he kind of walked over
to me and my teammate, Tao.
And he essentially sent us
like a follow-up email later.
And he explained
that we are using
this system for medical
question-answering
and summarization.
But he also thought that you
could use large language models
for another kind of application.
So his idea was essentially
that because LLMs
are trained on a lot of
scientific and medical tokens,
you could actually prompt it
to do hypothesis generation.
For example, he
wanted to actually use
it to identify causative gene
factors for rare diseases
and so on and so forth.
So it was an interesting idea.
But back then, we were
still dealing with our PaLM
class of models over here.
So for those of
you who don't know,
PaLM is the precursor to Gemini.
And I hope that some of you
are at least using Gemini.
Trust me, it's good, maybe
not as good as ChatGPT or--
I'm kidding, but you
guys should try it.
So it was like the
precursor to Gemini.
And Gemini itself is now
three generations old.
So at that point of
time, it was still
struggling to get reliable
answers from the system.
There would be hallucinations
all over the place and things
like that.
So the idea that you could
use an LLM-based system
to do something like
hypothesis generation,
it kind of felt wild,
because hypothesis generation
and coming up with novel,
creative scientific ideas
is squarely in the realm
of expert scientists.
And to think that you could
build out like an AI system
to do that, it felt like
many, many years away.
So I actually went
back to my team
and I asked, should we do
this project right now?
And the overwhelming
feedback was that we're
just not ready for it yet.
But sometimes, the
best projects--
and I think you probably
all have experienced this.
But for me, certainly,
I think some
of the best projects
that I've worked on
are essentially examples
where we actually don't how
to reach the end
goal, but we still
decide to just go
ahead and do this.
So this was one of those kind
of projects where we did not
know exactly how to clearly
approach this problem,
or what was going to be like
a solution that would lead us
to this end goal?
It's almost like you
jumping off a cliff,
and you have to figure out
building out a flying machine
or an airplane on the way down.
So this project is
an example of that,
where we just decide to
go ahead and do this,
and we just try to, OK,
let's construct some evals.
Let's make some progress.
Let's just see how
far we can push.
And that's what
we continue to do.
So what we initially
did was just
using our PaLM-based system.
We put together like
an agentic scaffold.
And remember, this
is all like 2023.
The word "agent"
was not being used.
But we still put
together this scaffold,
which had access to some
databases and some tools.
And it could go and
retrieve that information.
It could read that
literature up.
And then we would ask
it to predict, OK,
what are maybe the most likely
genes to cause this rare disease
variant, and things like that.
And we started doing that.
And we actually even saw
some promising results.
So there was this one
particular hypothesis
that this system came up with
that actually Gary went on
to validate in his lab
using these CRISPR knocking
experiments on mouse.
And it turned out
to actually work.
And that ended up being like
a peer-reviewed paper that
was published in Advanced
Science a few months back.
So that was like promising.
But in the process of doing
that, we also realized,
what are the limitations
of using LLMs
in a naive manner for this
hypothesis generation task?
And if I were to summarize
it or put it crisply,
I would say that when you're
traditionally using LLMs, say,
Gemini or ChatGPT or Claude, I
would argue that these models
are primarily doing
system 1-style thinking.
So they're like coming up
with very fast responses.
So they're akin to coming up
with very intuitive responses
without deep thinking.
So it's mostly responses with
surface-level correlations
and pattern-matching
and things like that.
So that's helpful.
But at the same
time, when you think
about the kind of thinking
that is needed for science
and scientific discovery, it's
actually a very different kind
of thinking.
So you would notice that it's
actually a lot more slower.
It's actually more deliberate.
It's rigorous.
And I think you all might
have experienced that,
but when you talk to some
of the best scientists,
they'll tell you that they've
had their best ideas when
they've been thinking about a
problem for weeks or months,
sometimes even like years.
So they'll tell you that, I've
always had this thing going on
in the back of my head.
I've been thinking about this.
And suddenly, I had this nice
creative aha moment over here.
But essentially, the point
is that that's actually
a very different
kind of thinking.
So it's more like
system 2-style thinking.
And I think that
thinking is really
like the hallmark of science and
scientific discovery over here.
So the key research
question for us was,
how do we build out these
AI systems that can actually
perform this structured,
rigorous scientific thinking
that is really the
hallmark of science
and scientific discovery?
So that's one framing
of the problem.
Another way to
think about this is,
if you want to, say,
build out like a truly
scientific
superintelligent system,
how would you
progress over there?
How would you quantify progress?
So for that, I have
this graph over here.
And on the y-axis, you'll see
different scientific tasks
ordered by complexity.
So they range from things
like literature review
and hypothesis generation
to more complex tasks
like writing a research paper
or coming up with a PhD thesis
to something that's at
the highest levels, which
is coming up with
paradigm shifting theories
and breakthroughs, say, like the
general theory of relativity.
And then on the
x-axis, I have the time
it might take an
average human scientist
to perform these tasks.
So it can range from
something minutes and hours
to days, weeks, months, years,
and sometimes even decades,
and lifetimes to really
do paradigm shifting,
like research and theories.
And then if you were to start
asking this question, where
do some of the popular
AI models and systems
that we have around us--
where do they actually fall
onto this graph or this plot?
So a very popular
example is AlphaFold.
So if you were to think,
where does AlphaFold
fall on this graph?
So you'd see that I
have it over here,
which is at the extreme
end of the x-axis.
So if you ask me like, why
do I have it over there,
I would argue that
AlphaFold has, in some ways,
it's already done
the work that's
equivalent to millions of human
scientists years worth of work.
And then, if you
come and ask me why,
you just have to think
back to the status quo
before AlphaFold existed.
So before AlphaFold
existed, to get
to the structure of
a single protein,
that was often an entire PhD's
worth of effort over here.
So it would almost take three to
five years of dedicated PhD work
to get to the structure
of a single protein.
And then literally once
AlphaFold, the model
was developed and the system
came online, literally
overnight, we have predictions
for millions of protein
literally overnight.
So if you were to
think about that,
it's done the work
equivalent to millions
of years of human
scientists worth of time
and effort over here.
So that's very cool, obviously.
And it was recognized with the
Nobel Prize for that reason.
But at the same time, if
you look at this graph,
you'll actually notice that
I actually have AlphaFold
outside of this graph.
And the reason for
that is, at least when
I think about a scientific
superintelligent system,
I actually think about
generality being a very
important property over here.
And again, if you
were to ask me,
I would say that the one thing
that AlphaFold doesn't have
is this property of generality.
So it's like a very
specialized model.
So the only inputs
that it recognizes
are protein sequences, and the
only outputs that it can produce
are protein
structures over here.
So if you were to give
it like any other kind
of scientific problem,
then it wouldn't
be able to make sense of it.
So in that sense, it's a
very, very specialized system.
And it's obviously
very, very useful.
And it solved like
a grand challenge
that dated back decades.
So that's why the
system was recognized
with a Nobel Prize over here.
But at the same
time, it's an example
of a highly capable but a very
specialized system over here.
But if you want a truly super
intelligent system over here,
you would want this
property of generality.
And what do I mean
by generality?
It is just the ability to
take literally any problem
and figure out a way
to make progress on it.
So you may not necessarily solve
it, but what you would want
is your algorithm to be
able to make sense of it,
understand it, break
down into steps,
and make reasonable attempts
towards solving them over here.
So that is what I
mean by generality.
So again, I don't
know how many of
you have seen this Thinking Game
documentary, which chronicles
the history of DeepMind,
starting from its founding
to AlphaGo to AlphaFold.
So if you haven't seen
it, I would definitely
recommend seeing that
documentary over there.
And in that documentary,
there's one clip
where they actually show
IBM's Deep Blue machine
taking on Garry Kasparov.
So this was all back in 1999.
So obviously, Deep
Blue was able to beat
Gary Kasparov over there.
But actually, Demis Hassabis
was like the CEO of DeepMind.
He actually makes
this comment, which
I thought was quite insightful.
So what Demis says is that he
was actually more impressed
by Garry Kasparov rather than
by Deep Blue in that sequence.
And the reason for
that is just simply
that Garry Kasparov's brain
was remarkably general.
So it was able to
not only compete
with this giant black box
of a machine in this very
complex game like
chess, but it was also
able to do everything
else that humans can do.
So Garry could talk
in multiple languages.
He could appreciate art.
He could think about physics
and philosophy and poetry
and whatnot.
So the human brain has
this remarkable property
of generality.
And that, in turn,
allows it to do things
like science, come up
with creative hypotheses
for complex scientific
problems and things like that.
So in many ways, you
could even argue and say
that so far in the entire
universe, the only existence
proof that we have
for a machine that
is capable of this
kind of generality
and this kind of hypothesis
generation capability, that's
actually just the
human brain over here.
So the question
for us is, can we
build out like an AI system
that can mimic this capability?
So that's the core problem.
So if you were to ask--
we're talking about
generality over here--
what is the key building block?
And again, I would argue that
the key building block over here
is actually language
and natural language.
Because if you have
natural language
as an input/output interface,
much like we humans do,
we might be able to
understand different concepts,
and we might be able
to make sense of it,
and we might be able to solve
different problems over here.
So that's a great starting point
because the large language model
systems that we have
around us, they're
all built on this paradigm
of natural language input
and output.
So if you were to think about
Gemini or Claude or ChatGPT,
I'm sure you're
all talking to it
about a whole bunch of topics.
I'm sure many of you
are using to understand
your lectures, your homeworks,
but also things like physics
and philosophy and poetry and
whatnot, a whole array of topics
that you talk to this.
And these models, obviously,
are able to understand it
and interpret it.
So that's a good
property because they
have this generality notion.
So you can post to
it like questions
about any scientific
problem and hopefully
that they will be able to
understand and make sense of it.
But at the same time, maybe even
at least until say a few months
back, I think the
amount of evidence
that we have about these
LLM-based systems, the kind
of scientific tasks
that they can do,
I would argue that it's
still very, very early.
I'm sure many of you have
been using these deep research
modes of these systems to do
things like evidence synthesis
and literature summarization
and things like that.
But in terms more complex
scientific tasks, say,
hypothesis generation or
writing research papers,
we've not seen any
evidence of that.
So in that sense, there's
a lot of dark space
or blank space in this plot.
So there's a lot of room
for us to make progress up
and to the right over here.
So the goal for us with
the co-scientist effort
was simply just that, can we
build our AI systems that are
provably making
progress on this plot up
and to the right over
here, so essentially
perform more complex scientific
tasks over longer-time horizons?
So hopefully, that framing
is helpful in terms of what
we're trying to accomplish.
So in order to do this, in
order to build out this, say,
structured scientific
thinking engine,
the approach that
we took actually
borrows from the
rich lineage that we
have at Google DeepMind
over the years.
So if you go back to AlphaGo,
and so this is the 10-year
anniversary of
AlphaGo over here--
so you would see that AlphaGo,
the way it was developed,
the key principle was
this idea of self-play.
And to state it in a
very simplified manner,
the key idea was that
you had agents playing
against each other
in this environment,
and depending on the outcome of
the game, which was obviously
this game of Go over
here, the agents
would receive these
reward signals.
And then based on the
reward, the winning moves
or the decisions or
the strategies that
led to the winning moves
that they would get
reinforced in the
weights of the network.
And then the ones that,
say, led to the defeats
would get deprioritized
in some sense.
So that was the key idea.
So it's a combination of
self-play with reinforcement
learning and search.
And essentially, the beauty
of AlphaGo-- essentially,
or actually, it was
more like AlphaZero,
was the fact that you could
create this environment.
And in this environment,
you could just
have agents go against
each other using
this self-play setup.
And this setup actually scales
remarkably with compute.
So there's no human
interference over here.
You could just start
the agents from scratch.
You could set up
this environment.
And if you give the right
kind of rewards at the right
time, what you
essentially see is
that these agents keep on
improving over a period of time.
And then at the end
of, say, three months--
that was actually how long like
AlphaZero was trained for--
the system became
superhuman over here.
So that's a pretty
remarkable property to have.
Essentially, throw
compute at a problem,
and your algorithm
is just so good
that you don't have to do much.
You just let that system
run for a period of time,
and then it becomes
superhuman at this task.
Isn't that awesome?
Isn't that wonderful?
So like the question
for us, now how
do we take that approach,
that idea of self-play,
and apply it to more
complex domains over here.
So we started with Go,
and then in 2019 and 2020,
people showed that you
could have these systems
with a very similar
approach work in more
complex environments like
AlphaStar, for example.
But games are useful.
They're useful testbeds for us
to develop learning strategies
and algorithms, but you want to
apply these agents and these AI
systems and develop them for
more complex real-world tasks,
such as scientific discovery
or in medicine and things
like that.
So pretty much that's
what we've been doing.
Over the last few
years, the areas
where we've been applying these
systems, like the complexity
of the board games
and the environments,
that's just become
more and more,
I would say, sophisticated
over here, essentially.
So they've kind of
evolved to become
like the realms of medicine
and scientific discovery
and so on and so forth.
So the way we generalize
the idea of self-play
to scientific reasoning and
scientific discovery over here
is through this notion of
scientific debates and self
debates.
So what we have within
our agentic setup--
and I'll talk about that in
more detail in the next slide--
is essentially like
a team of agents.
And we have these agents
continuously engage
in debates with each
other over here.
So they continuously generate
scientific hypotheses,
but they also refine and
review and critique each other.
And we let this process go
on for a period of time,
and we continuously introduce
net new knowledge and reward
signals.
And using that reward
signals and using
this net new
information, the system
is able to self-improve
itself towards
better-quality scientific
hypotheses over here.
So that's the key idea.
So we just let this process
of self-debates or scientific
debates happen for
a period of time.
And then the composite
AI system that
emerges from this
multiagent setup
is actually capable of
scientific hypothesis generation
and the ability to solve
complex scientific tasks
over long-time
horizons over here.
So hopefully, that's
helpful framing.
And in this slide,
I have a deep dive
of the architecture of this
multiagent setup over here.
So co-scientist, I
would say, is one
of the first examples of a
general-purpose multiagent
system for scientific discovery.
And again, there's a lot of
text over here, but trust me,
it's actually quite simple.
And as I mentioned
before, the mission
was to build out a collaborative
AI system or a partner
for scientist over here.
So we imagine that the human
scientist would always be
at the driver's seat over here.
So they would be the one who
would be guiding the system.
So that's how the input/output
interface is set up.
So it's all set up
in natural language.
So what that means is
that you can literally
post to it any kind of
scientific problem over here.
So the way that happens is
the scientists can come in
and they can specify
this research goal.
So this can be quite short,
or it can be quite long.
So you can add in
all the details
that you want about
the scientific problem
that you want to solve.
And the idea is to
give as many details
as you need to the
system so that it
can do a good job of coming
up with the right kind
of hypotheses or solutions
that we want over here.
So in addition to
the research goal,
the scientists can
specify, for example,
what are some of the
constraints that the system must
satisfy in the solutions
that it generates?
What might be, say,
some axes or rubrics
to, say, rank different
comparable hypotheses over here?
They can also articulate some of
the preferences that they have.
But not only that much like,
say, your PhD supervisor
might tell you, go and explore
this initial direction over
here, the scientist can say,
OK, this is the problem,
but I think the solution
might lie over here.
So go and figure
this out essentially.
So they can give the system
initial like seed directions
to explore over here.
And again, they can also
give additional form
of multimodal data over here.
So it can be PDFs of
related publications
and things like that.
It can also be additional
experimental data over here
that you might have
generated in the lab.
So essentially, that
all forms the context
that is needed for
the system to perform
its hypothesis generation task.
So that's all structured and
set up as this research goal.
And that's the
input to the system.
And then what the system
does is it kind of does
a bunch of computation.
And as I said, this is dynamic.
So it can go on for as
much time as you want.
So it can go on for say a
few minutes, to a few hours,
to sometimes even
days and weeks,
depending on the complexity
of the problem here.
And at the end of that what the
system produces is essentially,
I would say, a research
report with a bunch
of hypotheses or
solutions towards solving
the problem that the scientist
had articulated over here.
So again, the interface
is very simple.
It's a research goal in and
research proposal or research
summary out with a bunch
of hypotheses or solutions
to solve the problem.
And then within the
system, as I said,
it's like a multiagent system.
And the way these
agents are configured
are essentially to
continuously generate
different kinds of
scientific hypotheses,
but also review, critique,
rank, and prioritize them
over a period of time.
And these agents
are all essentially
our latest and greatest like
Gemini models over here.
And we set them up with
different kinds of strategies
and system prompts.
So we force them to do some
very specific specialized tasks
within this multiagent setup.
So again, there's
a bunch of texts,
but I would say
that the simplest
way to think about this
system is to essentially
think about it a computer
program with a while loop.
So there's one
function or one method
which corresponds to
continuously generating
different scientific
ideas and hypotheses.
There's another function
to review and critique
those hypotheses over here.
There's a third function to rank
and prioritize these hypotheses.
And then there's
a fourth function
over here, which is to improve
and evolve those hypotheses.
So it's like a while loop
with these four functions
that are kind of running
asynchronously and continually.
And all these functions are
implemented using agentic LLM
approaches over here.
So as I mentioned,
each of these agents
have their own system
prompt set up over here.
So we call this a
library of strategies.
So we give each
specific agent a set
of strategies that can select
from to perform like the tasks
that it has been given.
So, for example, to
generate scientific ideas,
one strategy is to go
read all related research
papers to that
given goal, and then
use those research
papers to build up
a foundation of knowledge,
and then use that to propose,
some idea over here.
Another strategy to come
up with scientific ideas
is to simulate this debate.
So I think some of you
might have also experienced
this where sometimes
you get your best
ideas by talking to a friend.
So you both start off
with some initial ideas,
but then you have a back
and forth conversation.
And then what
emerges out of that
is an idea that is much better
than what you had both initially
to begin with.
So we try to simulate that
within an agentic setup
over here.
We asked the agent to simulate
an interaction between two
experts.
Let it go on for a few
turns of conversation.
And then at the
end of that come up
with a scientific idea or
a hypothesis over here.
So essentially, there's hundreds
of difference of strategies
over here, like
within each agent,
including the [INAUDIBLE] agent.
And in fact, one of the favorite
pastimes of all our team
members is essentially that
they would spend time listening
to these podcasts from,
say, Terence Tao or David
Deutsch and others.
And they would see,
how are these people
thinking in an abstract manner?
How are they coming up
with new scientific ideas?
And then they would try
to abstract and summarize
them and implement them
as a prompt within this
library of strategies
that we have.
And it's a continual evolving
body of knowledge over here,
so you can keep on adding it.
And then at test time, you just
have to sample one strategy
and then use that to generate a
scientific hypothesis over here.
So similarly, we have a
bunch of these strategies
for the reflection agent,
which is essentially
doing like this review.
And then the agent that
I want to maybe spend
more time on over here is
actually this ranking agent.
So what this agent does
is it kind of takes
the hypotheses and the ideas
that have been generated so far.
And then it kind of tries
to rank and prioritize them.
And the way it does that is
using this debate mechanism
that I mentioned before.
So what it does is it
orchestrates these debate
matches between these ideas.
And then it tries to simulate
a few turns of conversation.
And then essentially, the
goal is to rank these ideas
and say, which one is
better based on the criteria
that the scientist had
articulated initially
in their research goal?
So that's the setup.
So it does these
scientific debates.
And once you have a few of these
debates set up and run, what
you can then start doing
is you can actually
start like computing
these Elo scores.
So much like in a Go or
in a chess tournament,
you can use the Elo ratings to
and rank players, similarly,
you can take the same
approach over here
and use that to
rank and prioritize
the different scientific
hypotheses over here.
And what purpose it serves
is essentially this.
So if you were to simply have
only a generation or a review
agent within the
system, then I think
what that would end up
being is a system that's
generating many, many like good
ideas or decent ideas over here.
But I would argue that
that's actually not
enough to move the needle in
terms of scientific discovery
over here.
Because when you're
talking to scientists,
you would see that
they're actually
not short on ideas over here.
The expert scientists
have more ideas
than they have time
and resources for.
So if you like
truly building out
a collaborative partner
for these scientists,
then you have to respect their
time and their attention,
and only surface ideas that
are really worth their time
and their attention over here.
So you have to do a very good
job of prioritizing the outputs
from the system, really
summarizing them,
and also have this notion
of epistemic humility
within the system.
And when I say epistemic
humility, what I mean
is that the system should
be able to really convey
when it actually
doesn't about something.
So it should be able
to clearly articulate
what is its confidence
about a given hypothesis
and also say, what are
the key uncertainties that
need resolving over here?
So that is what this
ranking agent tries to do.
So it essentially tries
to prioritize these ideas.
It tries to say, which one is
better and which one's spend--
is worth spending like
time and attention on.
And it also tries
to compute, what
is the uncertainty associated
with each idea over here,
and propagate that
to the scientist.
So that's one purpose
that it serves.
And then the second
purpose that it
serves is essentially, because
these debates are all happening
in natural language,
what you can do
is you can create
summaries of them.
And then you can put
all of those summaries
back into the overall
memory of the system.
And then what happens is the
next time any of these agents
are doing their work, what
they can do is they can use--
read this summary
from the memory
and then use that to, say,
come up with better hypotheses
or do a better job at generating
reviews, and so on and so forth.
And what that helps is it
creates this nice feedback
loop in the system that leads
to a self-improving cycle
over here.
So that's the crux
of the computation.
So as I said, it's quite simple.
It's a while loop with
four methods over here.
And if you were to zoom
out and think about it,
it's almost like, I would
say, an agentic in silico
implementation of the
thought process that
happens in a scientist's
head when they're
trying to come up with
say new scientific ideas
and things like that.
And then once you let this
computation go on for a set
period of time, and
that depends on when
you reach your end state--
and again, there's a
few mechanisms in which
you can reach this end state.
So one way could
be like, you say
keep on going until you
have x number of ideas
or another method could be like
you could just tell the system,
maybe just stop when you can
no longer solve the problem
or you're stuck over here.
So once the system reaches
that end state, what it does
is it visually clusters all
the ideas that it has explored
so far and then puts all of them
together into this nice summary
doc, which in turn is then fed
back to the scientist over here.
So that's it.
So that's the crux
of the system.
And as I said,
again, all of these
are agents implemented using
our latest and greatest Gemini
models, so they have
all the long context
capabilities, the multimodal
capabilities, the agentic tool
use capabilities, and everything
that we need over here.
Yeah, so hopefully,
this was helpful,
but maybe I'll stop
over here right now
and maybe take a few
questions, because I
thought that was quite meaty.
Anyone?
Yes.
How is the reward systems Go?
How would you evaluate whether
a hypothesis is good or not?
Even for scientists, different
people have different views.
How this agent system
could be evaluate
what's better [INAUDIBLE].
So that's the next
half of the talk.
But-- yeah.
25 different, but the only
co-scientist [INAUDIBLE]
in the 25 preprint--
system didn't really
see much performance,
saturation, or plateauing
with test time compute.
Have you explored the scaling
of that further [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
So yeah, we can--
sorry.
We can discuss that
in more detail.
So I think it comes down
to the class of problems
that you're working with.
So there's a class of problems
where the search space is
so big that if you
keep on throwing more
compute at the problem and
let the problem intelligently
explore the search space, then
it is very likely to come up
with better solutions.
So for those classes of
problems, essentially,
there's in some ways no limits.
So these classes of
problems are where you're
trying to optimize something.
So if you have a well-defined
fitness function,
then you can keep
on, in some ways,
optimizing it and making
it better and better,
as long as you
have more compute.
So for those
classes of problems,
we essentially do not see
much saturation over here.
So you can keep on
pushing the system.
But then there are going to be,
say, two classes of problems
that both extremes.
So there's one class where
the problem is so easy
that there's no point
in spending so much
compute over here.
Why do you want to spend,
say, millions of tokens when
it's just such a
trivially easy problem.
So it could be some retrieval
problem or something
that's extremely simple.
And then at the
other extreme are
problems that we just don't have
the knowledge today to solve.
For example, if you ask
the system to do, say,
build out a time machine, it's
not going to be able to do this.
So no matter how much compute
you throw at the system,
it's not going to
be able to do this.
But the good thing is
there's a large class
of problems in the middle.
So over there, you keep
on throwing more compute.
You keep on introducing
new information.
And essentially, you see this
very nice scaling property
where the system
is able to come up
with better and
better hypotheses
over a period of time.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] actual
[INAUDIBLE] what
types of science, all of
these different categories
not made up ones like a time
machine or it's a chemistry?
Yeah, so that's the rest--
I'll show you a few
validation examples
where we applied the system.
[INAUDIBLE] seems
like a very linear way
of scientific progress,
and I hope that falsify it.
And I wanted actual science
is can argue anarchy.
So we have a system where
you get a bunch of PhD theses
automatically, but
you never actually
get to the next level of
having a breakthrough.
There's a bunch of filling
the gaps, like research.
So how do you still
keep the human
in the loop to be
informed enough
to actually make the
breakthrough if that's
the [INAUDIBLE] achieve, or do
you not believe in that feeling?
Yeah, I think that's a very
good question over here.
So I think one of
the goals that we
have is to generate such
compelling ideas or hypotheses
that the human who is in
the loop, the expert who
is in the loop, they would
be kind of willing to drop
all their ideas that they
have and work on this one.
And if you're able to do
that enough number of times,
then that means that
your system is working.
And the hope is that leads to
more discoveries and hopefully
breakthroughs.
So yeah.
So that's the goal in some
ways, to just develop things
that scientists did
not think about.
And yeah, maybe all
of them don't pan out.
They don't work out because
that's the nature of science.
But yeah, the idea is to
keep pushing and generating
such compelling ideas that
scientists are incentivized
to go and try them.
But you're spot on.
I think we'll soon
enter this era,
or maybe we're
already there, where
there's going to be so
many compelling hypotheses
that actually the bottleneck
will be in the verification
and validation over here.
So that's the next step,
how do we prioritize them?
How do we allocate the
right amount of resources
and pick the best
ones for validation?
Sorry.
All these [INAUDIBLE] there
any specialization of models?
Yes, so there's no
specialization for science
per se.
They are essentially all our
Gemini models, but some of them
might use, say, a Flash variance
versus our Pro variance.
So it depends a little bit
on the nature of the task.
So if you're doing like a
review or a verification task,
then you might want to use
the Pro variance, which
are maybe a little
better at reasoning
and thinking over here.
Whereas if the task is a
little bit more simpler,
then you might want
to use a Flash model
just because you want to save
some tokens and reduce the cost.
Any other questions?
OK, great.
So over the next few
slides, what I will do is,
I want to walk you through
some examples of validations
of the system.
So if I'm saying that system's
capable of scientific discovery,
the real proof is to
validate it in the lab
and show that the hypotheses
are actually working out.
So the first example that I
want to highlight over here
is, it's actually more of
a recapitulation over here.
So what happened is, when we
were developing the system--
and this was back in 2024
during the Thanksgiving break.
So we knew certain
researchers at Imperial
who have been working
on this concept
of antimicrobial resistance.
So we reached out to
them, and we told them
that, hey, we're building this
system called the co-scientist.
Do you have any use cases
or applications for it?
And then essentially what
they told us was that actually
made a very important
and compelling discovery
related to this very novel
horizontal gene transfer
mechanism in bacteria,
which, in turn, is
responsible for
antimicrobial resistance.
But the crucial aspect
was that they're actually
not yet published it anywhere.
So they had the
data and they were
in the process of writing up the
paper, but the rest of the world
did not know about this
discovery or this breakthrough
over here.
So when we reached out to them.
They said, OK, we think a
good test of your system
might be to see what it
produces if you were to give you
the same research goal
that we've been working on
for the last 8, 10 years.
So essentially, their research
journey or their timeline
is captured on the
left-hand side over here.
And then on the right-hand
side is our experiment.
So they gave us
this research goal.
And we let the system
run for a couple of days.
And then we shared
the results back
with Jose and Tiago who
were the key PIs associated
with this research over here.
And maybe you can
just share from them
what they thought about
these research results.
I don't have internet
access, but it's fine.
But yeah, maybe I can just
tell you what happened.
So as I said, this was
during the Thanksgiving break
over here.
And when we shared the results,
literally 30 minutes later,
I get this email from Jose.
And he says, I need to
talk to you right now.
And I was like, Jose, hold on.
This is the Thanksgiving break.
I'll call you.
And then I end up calling him.
And then he was literally
like, no, hi, hello,
nothing like that.
And he was straight up, do
you have access to my email?
And the reason he
was asking that
was because he thought
that we were cheating.
He thought that we
were reading his email
and using that to guess
the hypotheses over here.
And then we had
to tell him that,
Jose, we do many
things at Google,
but we don't read your email.
And then he was
immediately like,
do you have access
to my ChatGPT?
Because he was using
ChatGPT to help him
write his paper over here.
And then we again had to
tell him, Jose, come on.
We're not friends
with OpenAI just yet.
But anyways, when--
so Jose's not
someone who gets easily
excited by things.
He's like a very
seasoned researcher.
So when he had that
visceral reaction,
I think that was the
first moment when
we felt that, OK, we were on
to something with the system.
Because at the beginning of
the talk, as I was telling you,
we were not at all
sure that this is even
possible at this point of time.
But when someone like
Jose had that reaction,
I think that is when we
thought, OK, maybe we
are on to something
with the system.
So since then, what
we've been doing is
we've been opening up
access to the system
to more and more scientists and
researchers around the world.
And I think what
we're starting to see
is this emergence of a new
form of AI-human scientist
collaboration over
here that's actually
leading to new insights and
discoveries and breakthroughs.
So for example, there were
certain physician scientists
at Houston Methodist
Hospital in Texas.
So they were able
to use the system
to identify new repurposing
drugs and combination
therapies for very
complex forms of cancers
like acute myeloid leukemia.
Similarly, Dr. Gary Peltz
over here at Stanford,
he was able to use the
system to first identify
new epigenomic targets
for liver fibrosis.
But not only that, he then went
back to the system, and he said,
give me an experimental
protocol to validate
this in my organoid setup
that I have in my lab,
and also suggest some new
drugs that can help me validate
this target over here.
So again, I'll show some
results in the next slide,
but that also worked very well.
And then finally, what we've
been doing with the system,
is actually doing
more and more complex
tasks like discovering
and engineering
like de novo proteins with
different kinds of activities
that we would want for a bunch
of different applications.
And over here,
the system's using
tools like AlphaFold and binder
design models, all in the loop,
and performing these
complex scientific tasks
over longer time horizons.
So this is just a snapshot
of the results from the drug
repurposing experiment
that we had.
So on the right-hand side
essentially, what you see
is a bunch of these IC50 curves.
So these are essentially
validations of the predictions
that the co-scientist had
for certain specific drugs.
And they were tested on a bunch
of these different cell lines.
And essentially, what these
curves are trying to see
is like, at what
drug concentration
are you seeing this tumor
inhibition activity over here?
When are you actually
killing the cancer cells?
And the lower the
concentration, the better it is.
And essentially,
what we're seeing
is across these cell
lines, the drugs
are actually working at
reasonable concentrations
over here.
So that's exciting.
And then the second thing is--
again, I just copy-pasted a
snippet of the novelty review
that the system had generated
for its own hypotheses
over here.
So what the system
had predicted was,
let's try this drug called
KIRA6 for AML over here.
But it was actually
quite calibrated
in its own sense of
novelty over here.
So it was very clear and said
that this is not completely
a breakthrough thing, because
there are other drugs that
work on the same pathway
or the same target,
and they've been tried in
the context of AML before.
So that gives me confidence
that KIRA6 will also
work because it works
on the same target.
But essentially, KIRA6 has
not been studied extensively,
and there's been no
clinical trials over here.
So that's why it makes
sense for you to try it.
So it's calibrated over here.
It's like grounding
its recommendations
on evidence and past literature
and so on and so forth.
So that's kind helpful.
And that's the reason why these
physician-scientists picked up
and ran these experiments.
So this one has the results from
the liver fibrosis experiment
that I mentioned.
So over here Dr. Peltz, he
took like four suggested drugs
from the system,
and he tested it
in his hepatic human
organoid setup.
So these are liver organoids.
And essentially, all the four
drugs over here, all of them
show very promising
antifibrotic activity.
And in fact, this one,
this suggested one
over here, this is actually
a well-known and safe
and FDA-approved
anticancer drug over here.
It's called vorinostat.
And the reason
this is interesting
is because it kind shows
the complementarity
of the human intelligence
and the AI over here.
So if you're a liver
fibrosis expert,
you may not be aware what's
happening in the cancer space.
So you may not be thinking
about all the therapies,
all the progress,
all the pathways
that people are researching.
Whereas this AI is kind of able
to go broad, and see what's
happening over there, and make
these unexpected connections,
and present that diverse
human viewpoint back
to the human scientists who
can then use their own judgment
and their deep
expertise to figure out,
does it make sense or not?
So in some ways, humans
have this deep expertise,
whereas this AI can go broad.
And if you're able to
intelligently bring these two
kinds of intelligence
together, then hopefully what
you would get, the
sum of the parts,
hopefully, that's much greater
than the individual systems
alone.
So this is a good
example of that.
So this is another
more interesting
a recent one over here.
And over here, what
happened is, there
were a few researchers based out
of the Sainsbury Lab in the UK.
So they actually had a bunch
of these AlphaFold structures
over here.
And they were trying
to figure out,
how do I actually analyze this?
How do I discover
anomalies in this data,
like which structures are the
ones that are worth paying
attention to over here?
So what they asked is--
they used the co-scientist
to build up this structural
novelty index over here.
So it's essentially a
bunch of these features.
And then they used
these features
to reanalyze the AlphaFold
structural predictions
and the data.
And what they were
able to uncover
was actually a completely
novel and previously
unknown a massive potato
immunoprotein over here.
So usually, what
plant biologists
assumed was that
most of these plant
immunoproteins-- they're
called resistasomes--
they'll have this
hexagonal shape,
whereas what this new
insight or this new analysis,
what it uncovered, was they're
actually much more novel
and massive immunoproteins.
So it's called 11-mer over here.
Essentially, that's
quite wild in some sense.
So this was, again, a preprint
that came out a few weeks back.
And I think this has quite
massive implications in terms
of decoding plant
immunity and how
that might impact agriculture
and global food security
and so on and so forth.
This is another example.
So this is where we
have co-scientist
using AlphaFold in the loop.
And what we have
it doing over here
is to design these
better Oct4 proteins.
So Oct4 is one of those
classic Yamanaka factors.
So these were the set of
transcription factors for which
Professor Yamanaka was
awarded the Nobel Prize back
in, I think, 2010
or 2011 over here.
But the thing with these
transcription factors
is, while they
rejuvenate the cell,
they can also cause tumors
and things like that.
So you want to have better
versions of these proteins that
have the same activity but
are more safe over here.
So that's what we
ask the system to do.
So we asked it to
predict and design
better sequences that
have the right activity
and the right
delivery properties
and so on and so forth.
So we asked it to use
AlphaFold in a loop.
And that's what it does.
So it makes a prediction
of a sequence.
It uses AlphaFold to look
at the structural stability
and then uses that to
refine it hypotheses.
And it does this in
silico a bunch of times.
And then what we observe
is the final sequence
that emerges that actually
has the right kind of activity
that we're looking for over
here and the right properties
that we're looking
for over here.
So we're doing a lot
of this right now.
We're taking and testing
all these de novo protein
designs in the lab,
and they're all looking
extremely promising right now.
So this is another example.
So this one's unpublished yet.
But over here, what we
ask the system to do
was to go read all
the literature,
look at all the data, and
then predict these new, say,
genetic factors or these
secreted proteins that
might actually take a cell
and rejuvenate it or reduce
the number of senescence
cells over here.
So senescence essentially
means your cell essentially
becomes so inflamed that
it doesn't divide anymore,
and it causes
disease essentially.
So you want to reduce the number
of such cells in your body
and then hopefully you can
reverse them back and make
them like younger and
be more reflective
of younger
individuals over here.
So that was what the
task that we gave.
So we told the system,
go find these novel
or unstudied genetic
factors and things like that
and just give us a few.
So that's what it did.
So it ran for a few days.
It gave us a list.
So we tested like a few of
them, and we compared it
with this positive
control, like Klotho,
which is very well studied.
And essentially, we see that
the AI-nominated factors,
they actually have the same
fold reduction in terms
of the number of percentage
of senescent cells over here
compared to this
positive control.
So essentially, if
there's a plays out--
we have to do more
experiments over here--
we might have some net
new rejuvenation factors.
And that would, again,
be extremely cool
if there's-- works out.
Yeah, and then maybe
another example
that I would want
to very quickly walk
you through is a case study
related to Alzheimer's disease.
So this is similar to the
antimicrobial resistance example
that I showed before, which
was also a recapitulation.
But over here, it's a bit
more complex in the sense
that there were certain
researchers at Mass General
Hospital.
And what they were
trying to do was
they were trying to study this
linkage between ACE inhibitors,
which are, again,
very commonly used
to treat blood pressure
and heart diseases
and things like that.
So essentially, they found
this very interesting thing
that people who are taking
these ACE inhibitors,
they actually have a heightened
risk for Alzheimer's over here.
So what they wanted
to do was they
wanted to understand
why is that reason.
So they did years of
experimental work,
and they were able to
come up with a mechanism
and a prediction.
So it had a very complex
nine-step cascade over here.
So what we asked the
AI to do was to--
we gave it the same problem.
And we asked it, what do you
think is the reason why ACE
inhibitors lead to increased
risk of Alzheimer's?
And essentially
what it did was it
recapitulated their entire
nine-step mechanistic cascade
over here.
But the cool bit was
it was not only that.
It also predicted
one of the key steps
that the scientists
had actually missed.
So again, to
simplify this a lot,
essentially the thing is, so
if you take ACE inhibitors,
they modulate this chemical
signal called bradykinin.
And that, in turn, leads to--
there's a receptor on the
surface of your brain cells
called this B2R receptor.
So it triggers
this B2R receptor.
And that, in turn, leads to
neurodegeneration over here.
So essentially, what the AI
said was that the missing link
was essentially this
link between bradykinin
and this B2R receptor.
So what these
researchers then did was
they went back to
the lab, and they
did this is a protein
stability assay, which is
called a chase assay over here.
And essentially, that missing
step was also, again, validated.
So AI was not only
able to recapitulate
what they had exactly
done, but it was also
able to fill in the
finer details over here
and complete their hypotheses.
And this is actually
a good example
of how this agentic scaffold is
actually better than baselines,
because what we did was we also
gave the same problem to Claude
and GPT-5.
And essentially, while
both those systems
were able to get this first step
and the high-level hypotheses
right, they were actually not
able to get the full details
over here.
So you really needed
this agentic harness
to be able to arrive at the
key details and the specifics
over here.
So that's again-- it's telling
you how this agentic harness is
actually helpful.
The time that you're
spending on verification,
coming up with the right
kind of hypotheses,
that is how you get to much
better results and genuinely
novel scientific
insights and discoveries.
And yeah, the last one I want to
very quickly highlight-- again,
one of the things that
I do, besides trying
to help improve the
system, is actually just
ask it interesting questions.
So one of the things that
I've been interested in
is this relationship between
neurodegenerative diseases
and cancer.
It's actually well known that if
you are an Alzheimer's patient,
you actually have much
lower risk of cancer.
So that's not
super well studied.
So what I asked the system
was to just go and read up
the literature and
then tell me, what
are maybe some
understudied pathways
that are very common in neuro
diseases, like neuro genes,
essentially, that might actually
be implicated in cancer as well?
So just tell me, these genes and
these specific forms of cancer
that we should go and look at.
So when I gave this prompt--
and this is the inverse
comorbidity problem.
So you have one
disease, and that
just reduces the
chance of you having
another disease over here.
And essentially, if you
were to identify enough
of these pathways,
they could also
be targets to build drugs for
those specific indications.
So I gave the
system this prompt.
And it came up with a
pair of genes over here,
which are common neuro genes.
So there was these two
genes called DHX9 and SRRM4.
And not only that,
it also told me,
if you want to
validate this gene,
you should reach out
to this professor
Dr. Filippo Bellagio
based in Germany.
So that's what I ended up doing.
So I just took the hypotheses,
and I wrote a cold email
to this professor.
And what he did was, he had a
bunch of whole genome CRISPR
screen data.
And he went back
and looked at it.
And essentially,
what he saw was that
in the context of small
cell lung cancer, which
is what the system
predicted, these two genes
were way overexpressed
compared to other forms
of cancer over here.
So essentially, the
hypothesis was right.
So again, that's
another cool example.
It's unvalidated,
but it's essentially
the system like making a
connection and surfacing it.
And that's leading
to new insights
and potentially discoveries
and breakthroughs.
So I'll maybe stop on this note.
So you can see some of the
results from the system.
So this is a snapshot of the
hypotheses that I generated.
Again, these reports are super
detailed, like 100-plus pages.
But you can see that it's all
nicely explained with images
and things like that.
And again, this is one
of the research contacts
that I mentioned.
It tells if you want to
validate this hypothesis,
you may want to reach
out to these people.
And it also tells you, what are
some of the unexpected things
that it discovered over here?
So that's the co-scientist part.
And maybe I can stop over here
and take a couple of questions
if you have any.
Have you tried playing around
with knowledge cutoffs at all.
So like talkie has
been getting press
lately, 13 billion
parameter model,
but only on pre-1931 text.
Can you predict stuff that
happened after the cutoff?
Yeah.
That's a good question.
So I think the
imperial example that I
showed was exactly one of them.
And even the
Alzheimer's one as well.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, I think it's
a bit difficult
to isolate corpuses like
that because there's
so much leakage--
Yeah, definitely.
--that's happening.
But one thing that we've
been exciting about doing
is, we're using the system
to predict future events that
might happen.
So for example, there's a
bunch of clinical trials
that are happening, predict
the outcomes of them.
And it has reasonable
success so far.
But again, it doesn't
have all the information
because a lot of this is
proprietary in nature.
So yeah, my intuition
is that if you
have the right kind of knowledge
but not fully revealing
the details, then this
could be extremely powerful
predicting clinical trials
and things like that.
And that could be very helpful.
But yeah, doing the experiment
that you're talking about put--
yeah, that's much harder
because of the leakage issues.
How do we take more
scientific system [INAUDIBLE]?
Because in the end, you
have more papers like,
peer reviews already
[INAUDIBLE] takes too long.
And ultimately,
papers are only going
to be read by other agents.
So isn't there a
better way to have
peer review system and a
knowledge base for other agents
to work on this, rather
than waiting, like,
nine months before [INAUDIBLE]
test and the science?
It's a great question.
And honestly, I don't
have a good answer to it.
We're obviously starting to see
a lot of AI usage in papers.
And I think it was just this
morning where arXiv came up
with this new policy that, if
you have hallucinated references
in your papers, then
they would block you
from using arXiv for a year.
But I don't think that's very
productive, in my opinion.
I think we have to
have better mechanisms.
And again, people are
using AI and peer reviews
and that can be helpful.
But the risk is, again, that if
you don't use it judiciously,
then you're going to favor only
certain kind of papers that
pass through this
filter or funnel,
and then you leave the
other topics unexplored.
So yeah, I think
so that is going
to be like an important
challenge over here.
Again, I don't
have a good answer.
I think there's
also things that we
can do to enable agents to share
the discoveries and information.
Maybe there's a need
for a science context
protocol over here.
There's need for formats
that can help you standardize
scientific data and how
they are generated, how they
are shared and decentralized.
So yeah, I mean, there could be
a lot of cool engineering work
that we could do.
But again, there are going to be
some thorny issues also that we
have to address with the
flood of papers that's
coming because
humans are not going
to be able to keep up with it.
Any other questions?
Yes.
So for the reports,
[INAUDIBLE] you mentioned that
around 100 pages.
Yeah, I just wonder
how, I guess,
humans going through the
[? doors ?] and trusting
[INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
So one thing we try
to do is-- again,
we want to have all the
details in the reports.
But we also tell
the scientists where
to spend time and attention on.
So we tell, maybe
this is like the most
compelling or
interesting hypothesis,
so you may want to
read them first.
But again, it's also
possible that the system
is too conservative.
So even if it thinks that
certain hypotheses are not
viable, they may be still
having some interesting clues
or some interesting insights
that might help the scientist.
So that's why we still
keep them in the report.
But we clearly
tell the scientist,
you should focus your energies
on this particular section
or this particular
path because that seems
like the most promising one.
And on the flip side, there
might be certain explorations
where the system just
comes back and says,
none of the ideas that I have
so far are going to work.
So you may want to
reframe the problem
or maybe focus your attention
on a subproblem and things
like that.
So that happens quite a bit
in mathematical problems
over here where if you
make it solve the full--
come up with the full
proof, then it breaks down.
But if you break it down
into the right steps
and the right chunks and have
the human work iteratively
and interact with it, then it's
able to make progress over here.
So again, we have all those
mechanisms set up in the system
to be able to do that.
For the case that you
just talked about,
you mentioned you
can run it overnight
or over a couple of
nights-- how many 3.1 Pro
or whatever tokens for
magnitude [INAUDIBLE]
how many agents there
are in parallel?
Yeah, maybe I'll tell you
once this is not recorded.
Any other-- yes.
You guys are just thinking
about [INAUDIBLE],
like in terms of bad actors
that might have [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, it's a good question.
So yeah, we have
different layers
of safety checks over here.
So there's one
that happens right
when the scientist is specifying
the prompt or the goal.
So over there, we
check and make sure
that it's not
something nefarious.
But oftentimes, you
can get around that.
You can phrase it
in different ways.
So what we also do is we
also monitor the ideas
that it's continuously producing
and the exploration that's
happening.
And again, if we see, say,
a percentage of the ideas
are getting into this unsafe
territory, and that's right now,
I think, set to 10%
of the ideas, again,
we halt the computation
and we tell the scientists
that there's an unsafe
research goal, essentially.
And then finally, again,
because these agents are all
based on Gemini, and that itself
has CBR and testing and things
like that has
happened, so we are
able to get some
of those properties
from within the
base model itself.
But yeah, you have
a multiagent setup,
the surface of where
things could go wrong
and where things could be used
in an improper manner, that
also expands quite a bit.
So we have to have this
multilayered approach
to safety essentially.
Unfortunately, I think that's
all the time we have for today.
But round of applause
for our amazing speaker.
[APPLAUSE]